Hudson River Valley Commission Collection: Records Relating to the 1965 – 1970 Surveys
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Hudson River Valley Commission Collection: Records Relating to the 1965 – 1970 Surveys
1955 – 1976
NPKMC-222-096
3.33 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Hudson River Valley Commission
The Hudson River Valley Commission (HRVC) was formed by Governor Rockefeller and his staff to regulate development along the Hudson River in 1966. This collection primarily consists of the findings from a series of surveys conducted by the HRVC between 1965 and 1970.
Collection Overview
This Collection consists of 2.75 linear feet of papers, photographs, and audiovisual materials created by the HRVC and the Hudson River Environmental. The collection contains approximately 4081 negatives, 782 black and white prints, 290 sheets of contact prints, 80 color slides, 32 color negatives, 13 color prints, and 67 pages of manuscript material relating to several surveys of the Hudson River conducted by the Hudson River Valley Commission, between 1965 and 1970. The collection also includes four open-reel sound recordings of HRVC meetings and symposia, 1969-1973; two cassette tapes of HVRC meetings, 1972 and 1976; and two other videotapes.
Acquisitions Information
The Franklin D. Roosevelt Library presented the records to the Marist College Archives in 2004.
Historical Note
In September 1962, the Consolidated Edison Company announced plans to build a pumped storage facility, the largest of its kind in the world, at Storm King Mountain near Cornwall, New York. The initial application for license to construct the plant was filed with the Federal Power Commission in January 1963. Some three years later the Hudson River Valley Commission was formed by Governor Rockefeller and his staff to regulate development along the Hudson River. Widespread public concern over the social and economic impact of urban sprawl, the deterioration of scenic beauty and natural resources along the Hudson and the economic stagnation of many riverfront communities led to the creation of HRVC. The Commission was directed by law to review proposed projects within its jurisdiction “which would destroy or substantially impair significant historic or recreational resources or bring about a major change in the appearance or use of the water in the Hudson River or the surrounding land.” As part of this directive the HRVC conducted surveys of the Hudson River between the years of 1965 and 1970.
The Hudson River Environmental Society took possession of the collection soon after the Hudson River Valley Commission was dissolved and added additional materials. The Hudson River Environmental Society preserved the collection until 1983, when they transferred it to the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Library in Hyde Park, NY.
The Hudson River Environmental Society (HRES), a nonprofit membership organization, was founded in 1970 to foster research on the Hudson River environment and related coastal areas, provide a forum for communication and cooperation among researchers, and make the results of environmental research available and accessible to concerned citizens and public officials.
HRES works to facilitate and coordinate research in the physical, biological and social sciences; environmental engineering; resource management; urban and regional planning; and other disciplines in the Hudson River region. Equally important, HRES serves as a channel of communication between the research community and researchers. HRES strives to ensure that the best possible information is available to those who potentially affect the environment. The Society's membership includes corporate members, individuals from major academic and research institutions, consulting firms, government agencies industries and conservation organizations concerned with environmental matters in the Hudson Valley region and interested citizens. The best known activities of HRES are its conferences and workshops on subjects of current environmental interest. HRES has organized topical meetings on such subjects as: PCBS, acid rain, dredging and soil disposal, the Hudson River fisheries, State Environmental Quality Review Act, freshwater and tidal wetlands, toxic and hazardous waste management, coal conversions, scenic and historic area preservation, energy and the future, and coastal revitalization and preservation.
Restrictions to Access
There are no restrictions on this collection
Collection is arranged into four series: 1. Photographs, 2. Recorded Media, 3. Publication, and 4. Oversized Materials.
Materials retain their original order.
Alexander Saunders Papers: Records Relating to the Storm King Case, 1962 - 1966
Hudson River Conservation Society, Inc. Collection, 1930 - 1980
Hudson River Valley Commission Collection: Records Relating to the Storm King Case, 1966 – 1967
- 1. Photographs, 1965 - 1975; 1; 1.66 Linear Feet Boxes: 1 - 5
  Series containes 4,081 negatives, 782 black and white prints, 32 color negatives, 16 color prints.
  Original order
  - Negatives - Marinas (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Manhattan NYC, 3/8/62 (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - Brooklyn NYC, 2/21/67 (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - New Baltimore T. (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - Athens V. (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Troy (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - Schaghticoke (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - East Greenbush (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - Castleton on the Hudson (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - Watervliet (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - Ravena (Folder 11, Box 1)
  - Green Island V. (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - Colonie Western Gateway (Folder 13, Box 1)
  - Cohoes (Folder 14, Box 1)
  - Coeymans, 2/67 (Folder 15, Box 1)
  - Albany, 1/15/70-12/25/68 (Folder 16, Box 1)
  - Saugerties, 4/67 (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - Esopus Meadows Lighthouse, 11/26/65 (Folder 18, Box 1)
  - Esopus (Folder 19, Box 1)
  - Hudson (Folder 20, Box 1)
  - Wappingers Falls, V. (Folder 21, Box 1)
  - Wappingers, T., 11/3/65 (Folder 22, Box 1)
  - Poughkeepsie T., 2/70 (Folder 23, Box 1)
  - Beacon, 11/9/65 (Folder 24, Box 1)
  - Tarrytown Lighthouse (Folder 25, Box 1)
  - Hudson Falls (Folder 26, Box 1)
  - Tarrytown, 9/70 (Folder 27, Box 1)
  - Kingston (Folder 28, Box 1)
  - Red Hook (Folder 29, Box 1)
  - Greenport (Folder 30, Box 1)
  - Estates, 8/1/68 (Folder 31, Box 1)
  - Easton (Folder 32, Box 1)
  - Cold Spring (Folder 33, Box 1)
  - Briarcliff Manor (Folder 34, Box 1)
  - Bannerman’s Island, 2/8/68 (Folder 35, Box 1)
  - Albany (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - Negatives 1-10 (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - Negatives 41-50, 3/7/67 (Folder 3, Box 2)
  - Fishkill (Folder 4, Box 2)
  - Negatives 31-40, 5/69 (Folder 5, Box 2)
  - Negatives 21-30 (Folder 6, Box 2)
  - Negatives 11-20, 2/70-5/70 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - Negatives 51-60, 5/68 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Negatives 121-130 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - (Negatives) 141-150 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - (Negatives) 131-140 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - Negatives 111-120, 9/23/70 (Folder 12, Box 2)
  - Agricultural (Folder 13, Box 2)
  - Quarries, 2/8/66 (Folder 14, Box 2)
  - Transportation (Folder 15, Box 2)
  - Urban Development (Folder 16, Box 2)
  - Haverstraw T., 2/15/66 (Folder 17, Box 2)
  - Barges - Sunken (Folder 18, Box 2)
  - Boating (Folder 19, Box 2)
  - Yonkers, 9/14/67 (Folder 20, Box 2)
  - Community Meetings (Folder 21, Box 2)
  - Fort Hunter (Folder 22, Box 2)
  - Historic Pictures (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - Highland, 11/9/65 (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - Highland Falls (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Cornwall on Hudson (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - Bear Mt. Bridge (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - Stony Point (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - Orange Garden Club Boat Ride (Folder 7, Box 3)
  - Helicopter Trip, 11/9/65 (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - Upper Hudson (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - Nyack (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - Human Interest, 5/68 (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - Junkyards (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - Catalogue, 1/13/66-2/13/66 (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - Public Hearings (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - Sewer Treatment Plants Water (Folder 15, Box 3)
  - Power Lines (Folder 16, Box 3)
  - Pollution - Hudson (Folder 17, Box 3)
  - Plant Life (Folder 18, Box 3)
  - Palisades, 10/22/55-9/21/59 (Folder 19, Box 3)
  - New Jersey (Folder 20, Box 3)
  - Mohawk River (Folder 21, Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 22, Box 3)
  - Little Falls (Folder 23, Box 3)
  - Dayline, 6/17/58 (Folder 24, Box 3)
  - Coast Guard, 4/67 (Folder 25, Box 3)
  - Chapell Hill Homes, 7/25/68 (Folder 26, Box 3)
  - Corinth T. (Folder 27, Box 3)
  - Mechanicville (Folder 28, Box 3)
  - Saratoga (Folder 29, Box 3)
  - Stillwater (Folder 30, Box 3)
  - Waterword T. (Folder 31, Box 3)
  - Negatives 71-80 (Folder 32, Box 3)
  - Negatives 61-70, 12/12/68 (Folder 33, Box 3)
  - Hudson Highlands, 10/28/65-2/8/66 (Folder 34, Box 3)
  - Newburgh (Folder 1, Box 4)
  - Philipstown, 11/9/65 (Folder 2, Box 4)
  - Negative 81-90, 8/70 (Folder 3, Box 4)
  - Ulster (Folder 4, Box 4)
  - Sneden Landing, 2/2/67 (Folder 5, Box 4)
  - Chester (Folder 6, Box 4)
  - Glen Falls (Folder 7, Box 4)
  - Cortlandt, 11/9/65-12/4/66 (Folder 8, Box 4)
  - Croton on Hudson, 9/70 (Folder 9, Box 4)
  - Hastings on Hudson, 7/70 (Folder 10, Box 4)
  - Ossining V. (Folder 11, Box 4)
  - Peekskill (Folder 12, Box 4)
  - Newburgh T. (Folder 13, Box 4)
  - Piermont (Folder 14, Box 4)
  - Negatives 91-100, 10/69-12/69 (Folder 15, Box 4)
  - Negatives 101-110, 10/8/65-2/8/66 (Folder 16, Box 4)
  - Loose Items, 9/28/70 (Folder 17, Box 4)
  - Sloop Hill From Cornwall NY, 2/7/66-2/8/66 (Folder 1, Box 5)
  - Snake Hill, 2/7/66-2/8/66 (Folder 2, Box 5)
  - Moodna Creek, 2/7/66-2/8/66 (Folder 3, Box 5)
  - Greenbush Rd., 2/5/66 (Folder 4, Box 5)
  - Quarry from Long Clove Rd., 2/5/66 (Folder 5, Box 5)
  - Haverstraw NY, 2/54/66 (Folder 6, Box 5)
  - Route 9W, 1/3/66 (Folder 7, Box 5)
  - Palisades Parkway Intersection, 1/3/66 (Folder 8, Box 5)
  - Western Gate, 11/29/65 (Folder 9, Box 5)
  - 9W Bridge, 11/28/65 (Folder 10, Box 5)
  - Esopus Creek Gorge, 11/24/65-11/26/65 (Folder 11, Box 5)
  - Abandoned Quarry, 11/14/65 (Folder 12, Box 5)
  - Old Stone Barn, 11/14/65 (Folder 13, Box 5)
  - Esopus Meadows Point, 11/9/65 (Folder 14, Box 5)
  - Quassaick Creek, 11/1/65 (Folder 15, Box 5)
  - Hemlock Point, 11/9/65 (Folder 16, Box 5)
  - Mirror Lake, 11/9/65 (Folder 17, Box 5)
  - Esopus Lake 11/9/65 (Folder 18, Box 5)
  - Wappingers Creek, 11/3/65 (Folder 19, Box 5)
  - Wappingers Falls, 11/3/65 (Folder 20, Box 5)
  - Newburgh, 11/1/65 (Folder 21, Box 5)
  - Breaknect Pt., 1/26/65 (Folder 22, Box 5)
  - Indian Brook, 10/29/65 (Folder 23, Box 5)
  - Foundry Brook, 10/29/65 (Folder 24, Box 5)
  - Lake Surprise, 10/29/65 (Folder 25, Box 5)
  - Lake Valhalla, 10/28/65-10/29/65 (Folder 26, Box 5)
  - Fishkill Creek, 10/28/65 (Folder 27, Box 5)
  - Aerials I, 6/10/65-12/7/65 (Folder 28, Box 5)
  - Canojoharie Creek, 12/7/65 (Folder 29, Box 5)
  - Big Nose / Little Nose, 12/7/65 (Folder 30, Box 5)
  - Western Gateway, 12/7/65 (Folder 31, Box 5)
  - Mohawk River, 11/30/65 (Folder 32, Box 5)
  - Mohawk Bottomlands, 11/30/65 (Folder 33, Box 5)
  - Fort Hunter, 11/29/65 (Folder 34, Box 5)
  - Aerials II, 8/10/74-7/29/75 (Folder 35, Box 5)
- 2. Recorded Media, 1964 - 1976; 2; 0.66 Linear Foot Boxes: 6 - 7
  Series contains 4 open reel sound recordings, 2 cassette tapes, 2 videotapes
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: Larry Birns Interviews, October 15, 1964, Benjamin Frasier and Charles E. Hoppin, unedited tape (Folder 1, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: Dr Eisenbud, HR Symposium, October 1969 (Folder 2, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: HRVC Steering Committee, February 17, 1970 (Folder 3, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 1” (Folder 4, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 2” (Folder 5, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 3” (Folder 6, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 4” (Folder 7, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 5” (Folder 8, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: “Tape 6” (Folder 9, Box 6)
  - ¼” Open Reel Audio Tape: July 6, 1973, Assessment Meeting (Folder 10, Box 6)
  - Audio Cassette: Hudson River Tidal Marsh Workshop/ Bard (Folder 11, Box 6)
  - Audio Cassette: Hudson River Tidal Marsh Workshop Tape 2 (Folder 12, Box 6)
  - Audio Cassette: HRES 11/16/1972 (Folder 13, Box 6)
  - 35mm Slides: Tourway Slides (Folder 1, Box 7)
  - 35mm Slides: Tourway Slides (Folder 2, Box 7)
  - 35mm Slides: Tourway Slides (Folder 3, Box 7)
  - 35mm Slides: Gil Tauber (slides) (Folder 4, Box 7)
  - ½” Open Reel Video Tape: 4th Symposium Hudson River Ecology (Folder 5, Box 7)
  - ½” Open Reel Video Tape: 4th Symposium Hudson River Ecology 03/1976, Tape2 (Folder 6, Box 7)
- 3. Publication, 1964 - 1972; 3; 0.33 Linear Feet Box: 8
  HVRC Recorded Media and Publications
  - Historical Quotes (Folder 1, Box 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 2, Box 8)
  - Publications (Folder 3, Box 8)
  - Photos Used In Publications (Folder 4, Box 8)
- 4. Oversized Materials, 4; 0.66 Linear Feet Boxes: 9 - 10
  31 oversized photographs, 1 glass slide
  - 4 x 3.25” Glass Slide: “Paper Bags” (Folder 1, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6” mounted photograph of Hudson River (Folder 2, Box 9)
  - 6.25 x 9.5” mounted photograph of Storm King Mountain on Hudson River (Folder 3, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6.25” mounted photograph of forest on Hudson River (Folder 4, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6.25 mounted photograph of Hudson River in winter (Folder 5, Box 9)
  - 8 x 6.25” mounted photograph of mountain on Hudson River (Folder 6, Box 9)
  - 8 x 7.5” mounted photograph of Upper Reservoir (Folder 7, Box 9)
  - 7.5 x 7.5” mounted photograph of brook in forest near Hudson River (Folder 8, Box 9)
  - 7.5 x 7.5” mounted photograph of waterfall in forest near Hudson River (Folder 9, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6.25” mounted photograph of West Point Ceremony on Hudson River (Folder 10, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 5.5” mounted photograph of “Break Neck Ridge” on Hudson River (Folder 11, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6.25” mounted photograph of railroad tracks along Hudson River (Folder 12, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6.25” mounted photograph of mountain on Hudson River in winter (Folder 13, Box 9)
  - 6.25 x 7.75” mounted photograph of mountain along Hudson River (Folder 14, Box 9)
  - 9.5 x 6” mounted photograph of factory on Hudson River (Folder 15, Box 9)
  - 5.75 x 7” mounted photograph of factory on Hudson River (Folder 16, Box 9)
  - 7.5 x 7.5” mounted photograph of forest near Hudson River (Folder 17, Box 9)
  - 7.5 x 7.5” mounted photograph of forest near Hudson River (Folder 18, Box 9)
  - 10 x 8” mounted photograph of Hudson River (Folder 19, Box 9)
  - 13 x 9” mounted photograph of mountains near Hudson River (Folder 20, Box 9)
  - 13 x 9.75” mounted photograph of Storm King Mountain (Folder 21, Box 9)
  - 6.5 x 4.25” mounted photograph of Hudson River (Folder 22, Box 9)
  - 18.75 x 14.75” mounted photograph of pollution on Hudson River (Folder 1, Box 10)
  - 19 x 14.5” mounted photograph of factory on Hudson River (Folder 2, Box 10)
  - 18.75 x 15.25” mounted photograph of explosion on abandoned railway bridge (Folder 3, Box 10)
  - 19 x 14.5” mounted photograph of billboards on road close to Hudson River (Folder 4, Box 10)
  - 18 x 15.5” mounted photograph of factory on Hudson River (Folder 5, Box 10)
  - 19.5 x 15.5” mounted photograph of sewage pipe on Hudson River (Folder 6, Box 10)
  - 10.75 x 15.25” mounted photograph of sewage pipe on Hudson River (Folder 7, Box 10)
  - 19.5 x 15.5” mounted photograph of sewage pipe on Hudson River (Folder 8, Box 10)
  - 15.75 x 18.15” mounted photograph of high voltage tower on Hudson River (Folder 9, Box 10)
  - 19.5 x 15.5” mounted photograph of factory on Hudson River (Folder 10, Box 10)